A Guide to the Architectural League of New York: Archive of Women in Architecture Record, 1892-1976, n.d.
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Architectural League of New York: Archive of Women in Architecture Records, 1892-1976, n.d.
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Architectural League of New York
Ms2005-016
5.2 Cubic Feet 4 boxes; 4 oversize folders
The Architectural League of New York created the Archive of Women in Architecture collection in 1973 to gather biographical and project data about women professionals in the field of architecture and other related disciplines. This information was used to create a 1977 exhibition and the book, Women in American Architecture: A Historic and Contemporary Perspective, edited by Susana Torre.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Architectural League of New York: Archive of Women in Architecture Records were donated to the International Archive of Women in Architecture at the Special Collections by the creator in 2002.
Historical Information
The Architectural League of New York is a non-profit organization that sponsors exhibitions, research studies, and projects that explore ideas in architecture and related art and design fields. The ALNY promotes excellence and innovation in architecture and urbanism by broadening the knowledge of these fields and communicating the importance of architecture in public life.
In 1973 the ALNY founded the Archive of Women in Architecture as a means to gather data about the careers of women in the field of architecture and other design professions. The project was made possible with public funds from the New York State Council on the Arts and a grant from the National Endowment for the Arts, and contributions from CBS, Inc., IBM Corporation, and Harry Winston, Inc. The archive committee consisted of Susana Torre, Coordinator, Phyllis Birkby, Regi Goldberg, Marjorie Hoog, Naomi Leff, Dimon Liu, Mimi Lobell, and Marita O'Hare.
In September of that year, the Archive began a national survey to collect both biographical and project data from women working in the profession. Committee members sent a form letter to women architects describing the archive and its mission, along with both a biographical worksheet and a project worksheet. At this time, Archive committee members also collected information about women who were no longer practicing architects in 1973. From the information gathered for the Archive, a 1977 exhibition and a book, Women in American Architecture: A Historic and Contemporary Perspective, were produced. The Archive of Women in Architecture ceased to collect material after this date.
Scope and Content
The Architectural League of New York: Archive of Women in Architecture collection consists mainly of copies of the form letters sent out by the Archive in 1973 and completed biographical worksheets, project worksheets, and other materials sent by women in reply to the solicitation. The form letter described the archive and its mission and was accompanied by a biographical worksheet and a project worksheet. The biographical worksheet includes information such as name, date of birth, address, telephone, education, awards, fellowships, grants, registration status, professional affiliations, work experience, areas of special interest and additional pertinent data. The project worksheet includes information such as project title, project category, project description, project data, participation in projects, and a place to list what media was submitted to the archive. Acceptable forms of project media included photos, photocopies, 35mm slides and written material not exceeding 8.5 x 11" when folded.
The amount of information about each woman architect in this collection varies because the selection of the materials was left to the judgment of the individual who submitted them. Some folders contain only a copy of the form letter from the Archive, while others include articles written by or about women, or photographs or blueprints of projects. If the folder title indicates "architectural projects," material includes an AWA project worksheet with supporting documentation of the projects, such as photos, slides or written information. If the folder title indicates "architectural drawings," the folder includes some form of architectural plans that accompany supporting documentation.
The collection also includes several publications that were donated to the Archive that deal specifically with working women, women in architecture, and architectural trends. Articles and booklets were retained in the collection, while full published works were cataloged individually. Removed items are listed below under Separated Items.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into two series. Most material is stored in legal size folders, but some oversized material is stored in a flat box (Box 4) and in oversize folders.
Series I, Records of Individuals, contains material about women architects arranged alphabetically by last name. It includes some oversized architectural plans.
Series II, General Information about Women and Architecture, is arranged chronologically by date of publication.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Additional material related to the 1977 exhibition and book Women in American Architecture is found in another IAWA collection, the Susana Torre Architectural Papers, 1976-2000, Ms90-016.
Separated Material
These publications were cataloged separately in the Addison library catalog, and are available through the Special Collections Reading Room:
SERIES I:
Curran, June. Drawing Plans for Your Own Home. New York: McGraw-Hill, 1976. Call number NA7115 .C87 1976
Cutler, Laurence S., and Sherrie Stephens Cutler. System Ecologic: Phase II. Cambridge, Mass., 1973. Call number TH1000.C98 S9 1973
Hosken, Fran P. The Language of Cities. New York: Macmillan, 1972. Call number HT153 .H65 1972
Kutsenkow, F. Corinne, Florence Carr Randall, and James J. Jones. Voices of Earth: Man's Environment. San Francisco: Leswing Communications, 1971. Call number GF48.K8 1971
Perriand, Charlotte. Charlotte Perriand: Interior Equipment. New York: Architectural League of New York, 1997. Call number NK2004.3.P47 C43 1997
SERIES II:
New York Cultural Center and Women in the Arts. Women Choose Women: January 12 - February 18, 1973. New York: New York Cultural Center, 1973. Call number N6512 .W59 1973
Index Terms
Subjects:
History of Women in Architecture; International Archive of Women in Architecture (IAWA); Women -- History
Contents List
- Records of Individuals, 1941-1976, mostly n.d.
  - Armstrong, Leslie: Curriculum vitae and architectural projects, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Aycock, Alice: Williams College project, 1975 (Oversize 1)
  - Batorewicz, Valerie: Architectural projects, 1967-1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bauer, Catherine: Short biography (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Beecher, Catharine: Short biography (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bennett, Rachelle: Firm brochure (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Berke, Judy: Project plans for the Penn residence (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Berkeley, Ellen Perry: Articles, 1966-1974 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Berkley, Sheila: Photographs of sculptures, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bertrand, Wendy: Biographical worksheet (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bethune, Louise: Research notes collected by the archive (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Birkby, Noel Phyllis: Photographs of studio built for David Jacobs (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Blackburn, M. Jane: Resume (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Blackwell, Linda: Biographical worksheet (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Blaumanis, Dace: Biographical worksheet (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Boutelle, Sara: Archive letter to Boutelle (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bowers, Garland T: Project information for Fonticello Gardens residential development, 1956-1974 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Boyer, India: Biographical worksheet (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Boyer, Mary-Louise
    - Architectural projects, 1967-1974 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Architectural projects, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Brady, Constance L.: Form letter (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Bradley, Susan: Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Bregy, Carol: Biographical worksheet (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Bresnan, Adrienne Green: Form letter (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Browning, Andrea: Architectural drawings, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Broz, Rose Aimee: Form letter (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Bruck, Phoebe: Biographical worksheet and resume (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Brudno, Ann: Form letter (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Burbank, Gertrude S.: Resume (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Bzik, Ann: Form letter (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Campas, Anna: Architectural project, 1969-1973 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Celinska, Maria: Article, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Chadeayne, Olive: Architectural projects, 1973-1976 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Chafee, Judith: Form letter (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Chase, Elizabeth: Student work, 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Chatfield-Taylor, Adele: Article, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Chatfield, Ayla K.: Architectural projects
    - 1962-1968 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Ch'en, Lena: Form letter (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Christoffer, Margaret: Biographical information (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Close, Elizabeth: Architectural projects, 1941-1974 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Coblentz, Dorothy: Biographical information (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Coit, Elisabeth: Architectural projects, 1931-1963 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Collins, Grace: Form letter (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Conway, Patricia
    - Articles and Mass Transit project materials, 1965-1970 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Master's thesis, "Street Life: A Photo Essay", 1972 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Journal articles, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Plan description for Morgan's Run residential development, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Morgan's Run development site plans, 1974 (Oversize 2)
  - Coplans, Patricia: Architectural projects, 1968-1972 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Crawford, Mary Ann: Application to American Insitute of Architects (AIA), 1949 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Curran, June: Architectural drawings, 1960-1970 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Cutler, Sherrie Stephens: Resume and office brochure, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Dabby, Stella: Form letter (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Davis-Lakeman, Sandra: Biographical worksheet (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - de Bretteville, Shelia: Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - DiFate, Helen: Form letter (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Donaldson, Ellen: Resume (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Driskel, Jean: Architectural projects, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Dry, Carolyn
    - Student work, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Plans for Como Elementary School and art work, 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - DuBose, Meda: Form letter (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Duerk, Donna: Biographical worksheet (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Duke, Katherine: Architectural projects, 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Duncombe, A. Jane: Architectural projects, 1956-1974 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Dunning, Ann: Biographical worksheet (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Durr, Ruth: Form letter (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Easton, Merle: Architectural project for a school, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Edelman, Judith: Architectural projects, 1960-1974 (Box 1, Folder 67-68)
  - Fisher, Jan: Form Letter (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Forrest (Watson), Claire: Biographical worksheet (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Frank, Suzanne: Print of article based on doctoral dissertation, "Michel de Klerk's Designs for Amsterdam's Spaarndammerburt" Nederlands Kunsthistorisch Jaarboek, c.1968 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - French, Helen: Biographical worksheet (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Friedman, Beatrice: Book photocopy, Better Housing for the Family, by Beatrice S. Friedman. New York: Women's City Club of New York, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Geise, Carolyn: Form letter (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Gerevitz, Rina: Resume (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Glanz, Amy: Form letter (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Glynn, Margaret: Biographical worksheet (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Goldberg, Regi: Resume (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Goldschmidt, Gabriela: Biographical worksheet (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Goldstein, Carol: Biographical worksheet (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Gray, Wanda C.: Biographical worksheet (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Green, Susan: Form letter (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Greenwald, Audrey: Firm brochure (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Griffin, Marion Mahony: Article, c.1972 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Hagen, Carol: Form letter (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Hall (Johnson), Jane: Biographical worksheet and firm brochure (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Halsband, Frances: Architectural project, 1966-1973 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Hann, Marlys
    - Articles, 1971-1973 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Preliminary design of the RCA Management Conference Center, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 21-22)
    - RCA Management Conference Center drawings and plans, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - RCA Conference Center design, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Harkness, Sarah Pillsbury
    - Biographical worksheet and articles, 1965-1974 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Architectural projects, 1968-1972 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Haigh, Pamela
    - Biographical worksheet (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Booklet, Ramapo Mountain: A New Community in Mahwah, New Jersey, by Garden Cities Development Corp., 1972 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Hayden, Delores: Form letter (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Hayden, Sophia: Research notes collected by the archive about the Women's Building at the 1891 World's Columbian Exposition in Chicago (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Heller, Catherine: Biographical worksheet (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Hemenway, Audrey: Article about ecological sculpture (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Herriman, Rosalin: Form letter (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Hersh, Anne: Architectural projects, 1970-1974 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Hitchcock, Charlotte: Architectural projects, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Hodgdon, Rosaria: Curriculum vitae, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Homsey, Victorine: Articles, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Hosken, Fran P.: Curriculum vitae and articles, 1970-1975 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Howe, Lois: Bibliography and project list (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Jacknis, Marlene: Master's thesis, "United Nations Expansion, Manhattan", 1971 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Johanson, Patricia: Booklet, Some Approaches to Landscape, Architecture, and the City, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Johnson, Carol R.
    - Biographical worksheet and firm brochure (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Architectural projects, including Lowell Model Cities program, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Johnson, Carolyn: Biographical worksheet and Women in Architecture: An Annotated Bibliography and Guide to Sources of Information, c.1973 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Johnson, Jane Hasting: Form letter (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Johnson, Olive: Biographical worksheet (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Kasuba, Aleksandra
    - Architectural projects, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Plans for Manhattan Community Rehabilitation Center (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Kagan, Ellen B.: Paper, "Brasilia, New Capital in the Wilderness", 1974 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Kerbis, Gertrude Lempp: Biographical worksheet and architectural projects (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Kiaulenas, Vassia
    - Architectural projects, including Kiaulenas Museum House, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Architectural projects, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - King, Isabel: Resume (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Klein, Judy Graf: Architectural projects, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Knowles, Alison
    - Resume and project worksheets, 1968-1972 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Computer printout list for project "A House of..." (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Kozak, Mary: Biographical worksheet (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Kramer, Etel Thea: Architectural projects, 1964-1973 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Kutsenkow, F. Corinne
    - Resume and article, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Play manuscript, Chiaroscuro (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Master's thesis, "Children and Architecture", 1949 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Laleyan, Marie: Architectural projects, 1969-1974 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Langhorst, Lois: Biographical worksheet (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Largent, Margie
    - Architectural projects, 1961-1974 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Architectural drawings (Oversize 3)
  - Lawrence, Megan: Form letter (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - League, Ellamae Ellis: Biographical worksheet (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Lee, Deborah: Biographical worksheet (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Lepp, Maxine: Architectural project (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Lichtblau, Lucy: Biographical worksheet (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Lobell, Mimi
    - Resume and articles (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Articles by Lobell about architecture, 1974-1975 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Lombana, Elvira: Form letter (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Long, Mary Jane: Biographical worksheet and architectural project (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Lucey, Lenore: Form letter (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Macko, Helen: Form letter (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Malloy, Dolores: Architectural projects, 1966-1972 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Marriott, Bett Kniseley: Biographical worksheet (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Martini, Elisabeth: Biographical worksheet and article, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Maurer, Laurie: Form letter (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Mazwell, Linda: Form letter (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - McAvoy, Amy: Biographical worksheet (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - McCormick, Ann Marie: Form letter (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - McManus, Anne: Biographical worksheet (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Merz, Mary: Project information for Creek Bend Heights residential development (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Miao, Nancy: Architectural projects (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Miller, Nory: Form letter (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Milligan, Carina: Articles about Connecticut architects, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Miss, Mary: Plans for a sunken pool, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Moore, Kathrin: Architectural projects (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Moore, Sandra: Class materials (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Morgan, Julia: Research notes collected by the archive (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Moser-Khalili, Moira: Form letter (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Moynahan, Elizabeth: Form letter (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Muir, Edla: Architectural projects (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Murawski, Lucille: Form letter (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Myers, Mary: Form letter (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Myhrum, Maglet: Form letter (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Neski, Barbara: Articles, 1968-1973 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Newburgh, Selma: Architectural projects, 1967-1973 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Newman, Judith York: Articles, 1965-1976 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Newton, Jean: Form letter (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - O'Brien, D. Susan
    - Biographical worksheet and proposed projects (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Architectural projects, 1968-1970 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Architectural projects, 1971-1974 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Campus development plan for Texas Christian University, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Interim Design Report to the National Museums of Canada and the National Capital Commission on an Investigation of Housing the NMC in the Proposed Cultural Bridge, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Plans for Tarrant County Junior College Northwest, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Architectural drawings, 1971-1974 (Oversize 4)
  - Paine, Judith: Resume and research notes on women architects, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Peddle, Juliet: Resume (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Perkins, Ruth: Application to the American Institute of Architects (AIA), 1949 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Pierce, Irene: Architectural projects (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Polsak, Sandra: Project information and development plan for MUND, the Model Urban Neighborhood Demonstration program in Baltimore, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Ramati, Raquel: Article, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Scott Brown, Denise: Curriculum vitae and articles (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Siris (Coombs), Jane: Architectural projects, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Vinciarelli, Lauretta: Biographical worksheet (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Willis, Beverly: Resume and architectural project (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Yowell, Linda: "Housing Goals and Policy Planning: The Mitchell-Lama Program in New York City," 1973 (Box 3, Folder 47)
- General Information about Women and Architecture, 1892-1976
  - Ladies Home Journal, July 1892 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Los Angeles Times, Home Section, featuring Women in Architecture (complete original section), January 23, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Los Angeles Times, Home Section (copies of articles), January 23, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    Scope and Contents note
    Shows work by Jean Driskel, Lucille Raport, Olive Chadeayne, and Lutah Maria Riggs
  - Booklet, The Arthur and Elizabeth Schlesinger Library on the History of Women in America, 1972-1974 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Progressive Architecture, August 1974 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Booklet, Rockefeller Family Fund Report, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - "Answers from Women Architects" in House & Garden Remodeling Guide, 136-151, Spring-Summer 1974 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    Shows work by Leslie Armstrong, Kirsten Childs, Susan Bragstad, Judith York Newman, Nancy Copely, Carol Bain, Judith Edelman, and Astra Zarina
  - Advertisement for Women's Organizations and Leaders Directory, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Journal of Long Island History, Vol. XI, No. 2, Spring 1975 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Directory of the Alliance of Women in Architecture, August 1975 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Progressive Architecture featuring Women in Architecture, March 1977 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - "Why Have There Been No Great Women Architects?" by Elena Bortein, in womanart, Vol. 1, No. 4, Spring/Summer 1977 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Women's Building calendar and program for Women's Caucus for Art, c.1977 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Poster, Women in Architectural Symposium at Washington University in St. Louis (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - "Columbus, Indiana: Architecture and the Quality of Life" by Elmer H. Johnson, from cultures, Vol. 1, No. 2 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Requests for use of the Archive of Women in Architecture, 1974-1976 (Box 3, Folder 60)